地          球          脉          动
我们陆地的边缘都是浅海域
Our planet's continents are fringed by shallow seas.
它们挨着大陆架 很少地超过200米深
Rarely more than two hundred meters deep they lie on the continental shelves
大陆架有时可能延伸达几百英里
which may stretch sometimes for hundreds of miles
再往下就是漆黑的深渊
before the sea floor drops into deeper darker waters.
尽管浅水域仅仅占据了8%的海洋
All together they constitute a mere eight percent of the world's oceans
不过大多数的海洋生物都生活在这里
but they contain the vast majority of it's marine life.
多        样        浅        海
画 外 音
大卫 · 爱登堡   爵士
一只雄性座头鲸正在用歌声吸引雌鲸来交配
A male humpback whale sings to attract a mate.
座头鲸刚刚回到它的热带地区的浅海繁殖地
The whales have just returned to their breeding grounds in the shallow seas of the tropics.
幼鲸才刚刚几周大
The calf is no more than a few weeks old.
虽然已经三米长,一吨重 还是比较虚弱,也容易受攻击
Despite being three meters long and weighing nearly a ton, he is nonetheless vulnerable.
不过幸好有妈妈照料
but his mother watches over him
疲劳的幼鲸被妈妈托上浮上水面好让它呼吸空气
and, as he begins to tire, she supports him close to the surface so that he can breathe more easily.
赤道附近的浅海是个非常理想的托儿所
These shallows around the equator are excellent nurseries.
温暖,平静,很少有掠食者
They're warm, calm, and contain very few predators.
顽皮的小座头鲸每天要喝500公升奶
The playful calf is now drinking five hundred liters of milk a day
但是它的妈妈却饿的要死
but his mother must starve.
在这里母鲸没有东西可以吃
There is nothing for her to eat here.
和多数热带浅海域一样
Like many tropical shallow seas
这片明净的水域实际上没有什么生机
these crystal clear waters are virtually lifeless.
虽然充满阳光 但是这里主要缺少浮游生物生长所需的养分
They receive year round sunlight but they lack the nutrients essential for the growth of plankton.
母座头鲸接下来要困在这里大约5个月
The mother will be trapped here for the next five months
等到小鲸足够强壮了,才开始到极地进食点的旅行
until her calf is strong enough to make the journey to the feeding grounds, near the poles.
珊瑚礁是荒凉海洋中的绿洲
Coral reefs are oases in a watery desert.
多数热带浅海比较荒凉
Most tropical shallows are barren
不过珊瑚礁汇聚着地球上四分之一的海洋生物
but these coral havens contain one quarter of all the marine life on our planet.
珊瑚礁是珊瑚虫的产物
Reefs are the work of polyps
一种象小海葵的有机生命群体
tiny colonial animals like minute sea anemones
可是它们生成的大堡礁甚至可以在月球上看到
yet the great barrier reef is so big it can be seen from the Moon.
大堡礁由超过2000个独立珊瑚礁组成
It's actually two thousand separate reefs that together
绵延在澳大利亚东北部海岸,长度超过1000公里
form a barrier stretching for over a thousand miles along Australia's northeastern coast.
不管有多大
Despite it's vast size
这里珊瑚礁也不可能容纳全部的海洋生物
this reef does not contain the greatest variety of marine life on the planet.
让我们去印度尼西亚的北部看看
For that one must travel north to Indonesia.
印度尼西亚的这些珊瑚礁 所容纳的各种鱼类几乎跟全加勒比海一样多
There are individual reefs in Indonesia that contain almost as many kinds of fish as live in the whole of the Caribbean.
而且珊瑚物种也要多十倍
There are also ten times the number of coral species.
珊瑚在一种微生植物的帮助下生长-海藻 是居住在珊瑚虫里的一种共生藻
Corals thrive in these waters with the help of microscopic plants, algae that grow within the tissues of the polyps
珊瑚虫利用触手抓食经过它身边的食物
and the polyps feed by snaring passing morsels with their tentacles.
到了晚上,共生藻停止工作 珊瑚开始释放更多的触手
At night, the algae are inactive but then, the polyps put out even more tentacles
这样,珊瑚虫可以昼夜不断地有效进食
so coral in effect feeds around the clock.
这种完美平衡
This well balanced alliance brings benefits
不仅有益于给珊瑚虫和藻类
to both polyps and algae and between them,
同时也把荒凉的海洋变成了绚丽的花园
they turn the barren seas into rich gardens.
印度尼西亚的珊瑚礁之所以 容纳了如此多的海洋生物
The Indonesian reefs contain such a variety of life
因为它处在一个巨大的十字路口
because they lie at a giant crossroads.
这里是两个大洋的交汇处 印度洋和太平洋
This is the meeting place for different seas the Indian Ocean and the Pacific.
在这里,每样物种都要仔细观察
Here everything demands a closer look.
在这株海扇上,有2只"珊瑚虫"不像珊瑚虫
On the surface of this sea fan, there are two polyps that are not polyps.
豆丁海马--全世界最小的海马,身长不到两公分
They're pygmy sea horses, the world's smallest, less than two centimeters high.
这2只雄性豆丁海马正在为争夺领地
They are males, settling a territorial dispute,
相互撞头攻击
by head butting.
电光灯?
An electric flash?
当然不是,这是火蛤蜊在表演
No, the display of a file clam.
蛤的肉质外壳的这种非常特别的规律性闪电
Perhaps this extraordinary pulsation of the clam's fleshy mantle
是在警告咬它的小鱼?
is a warning to frighten away nibbling fish,
不过真正原因无从知晓
but no one really knows
这里也有蛇 许多的蛇
And there are snakes here, too, lots of them.
这是巨环海蛇
These are banded sea crates.
它们在陆地上产卵,在水里捕食
They lay their eggs on land but they hunt here in the water.
它们直接捕食鱼速度跟不上
They're too slow to catch fish in a straight chase
因此就在珊瑚礁的裂缝和暗处寻找猎物
so they seek prey that is hiding in the nooks and crannies of the coral.
它的剧毒能立刻让受害者全身麻痹,动弹不得
Their bite is highly venomous and paralyzes their victims.
在这个珊瑚礁里,海蛇并不是单独行动
And on this reef the snakes do not hunt alone.
许多的黄色绯鲵鲣和它的同伴们 也在寻找同样的猎物
Shoals of yellow goatfish and trivali are seeking similar prey
它们引起了海蛇的注意
And they attract the snakes' attention.
它们也加入进来,开始扫荡珊瑚礁
As one group of hunters searches the reef they're joined by the other.
至少有30条海蛇加入到了这个队伍
At least thirty snakes have now joined the caravan.
大鱼将猎物吓到裂缝里
The big fish scare the prey into cracks
那里,海蛇就能抓住它们了
and there the snakes can catch them
这样从海蛇嘴里逃跑的猎物 也将直接送到这些大鱼嘴里
And anything fleeing from the crates will swim straight into the mouths of the waiting trivali.
猎物们没有地方可以躲藏
There's nowhere to hide.
有更多的海蛇加入进来一起扫荡珊瑚礁
As the raiders scour the reef, more and more snakes join the hunt.
这种鱼蛇之间的合作
This cooperation between snakes and fish,
引人入胜.只是最近才被发现. 因为它发生在偏僻的印尼珊瑚礁
spectacular though it is, has only recently been observed, for it only happens on the most remote reefs in Indonesia.
或许这种事情曾经发生在印尼的大多数珊瑚礁中.
Perhaps such hunting alliances were once a common sight
但是到现在 只有不到6%的珊瑚礁还还保持着原始状态
but today no more than six percent of Indonesia's reefs are in their pristine state.
在珊瑚礁上,是流砂的世界
Beyond the coral stretches a world of shifting sand.
这里无处可藏,要生存是很困难的事情
Out there with nowhere to hide survival is not easy
所以伪装变得至关重要
and camouflage can be crucial.
如果这个家伙不动的话 你说不定会以为这是块贝壳或者石头.
If this wasn't moving, you might think it was a shell or a rock.
实际上,它是条章鱼
In fact it's an octopus.
这条鲂鱼,它的巨大的胸鳍给它提供了很好的伪装
A gurnard. It's huge pectoral fins disguise it's shape
并且它的胸鳍还可以在找寻食物的时候清理砂子
and they can also help in clearing away sand when searching for food.
大颚鱼藏在地下.
The jawfish hides underground.
拟态章鱼用强有力的触手 摆出特别的姿势警告其他动物远离此地
The wonderpus octopus on the other hand has such a powerful bite that it has a special warning display to tell others to keep out of it's way.
植物设法到处生根
Here and there, plants manage to take root
它们成了绿海龟的食物
and they're cropped by green turtles.
海草是唯一在海里生长的有花植物
Seagrasses are the only flowering plants that have managed to grow in the sea
海草长出叶子状的带状物 以此延伸它们埋在沙子里的肉质根茎.
although they put out a few ribbon like leaves they produce very extended networks of fleshy stems, risomes, that are buried in the sand.
这种蓬勃的长势可以把海床覆盖在下面
At their lushest they can transform the sea bed into an underwater meadow.
世界上最大的草海在澳大利亚西部的鲨鱼湾
The largest expanse grows in the shallow waters of Shark Bay, in Western Australia.
这片广大的海洋牧场 面积可达1500平方英里
These vast aquatic grasslands stretch for fifteen hundred square miles
像陆地上的大草原一样 这里也养育了大量的食草动物--儒艮
and, like terrestrial prairies, they support herds of grazers -- Dugongs.
儒艮是海洋里最大的食草动物
Dugongs are the largest herbivores in the sea.
可以长到3米长,半吨重
They can be three meters long and weigh half a ton
它们除了海草什么都不吃 他们不停移动嘴唇,把海草的肉质根茎送到口中
and they eat nothing but seagrass, mostly the fleshy risomes, which they excavate with their mobile lips.
这群儒艮可以在一天内吃掉足球场般大小的海草
A herd can clear a patch of seagrass the size of a football pitch in a single day.
食物在热带海域的分布并不平均 所以要找到食物也不容易
Food is not evenly distributed in the tropical shallow seas and it can take a lot of finding
象宽吻海豚这种又好奇 又聪明伶俐又精神充沛的动物
but bottlenose dolphins are inquisitive, energetic,1 and very intelligent
发明了一种利用浅滩钓鱼的方法
and they have discovered a shoal of baitfish.
它们一起赶着海浪,好让海浪把它们带到浅水域
Together, they ride a wave, using it to carry them into the shallows
这样,捕鱼就轻松多了
and there, it will be easier to make the catch.
在澳大利亚西部
In Western Australia
这些海豚面临着一个巨大挑战
these dolphins have taken on an ever tougher challenge.
鱼儿们太靠近沙滩,而那里的水才几厘米深
The fish have taken refuge close to the beach where the water is only a few centimeters deep.
用有力的尾巴击晕猎物是海豚们常用的方法
Tail slapping is a method dolphins often use to stun their prey
不过在这里好像没有什么用处
but it doesn't seem to work here.
虽然已经很接近鱼儿了 急人的是还是差那么一点
The fish are tantalizingly close but they're still out of reach,
海豚于是开始用另一种技巧
so the dolphins try another technique.
用他们有力的尾巴加速
Vigorously pumping their tails, they work up some speed
如同水上飞机般
and then, they hydroplane.
这种速度让它们穿越最浅的水域, 来到了鱼儿那里
Their momentum carries them right through the shallowest waters, and onto the fish.
现在它们有搁浅的危险
Now they're in real danger of being stranded
但幸运来自勇气
but fortune favors the brave.
年轻的海豚在远处观看
Younger dolphins lie alongside, watching
不远处有8只海豚在展示这种高超的技术
but so far only eight individuals here have mastered this daring technique.
虽然多数热带海洋生物 聚集在珊瑚礁或者海洋牧场里
Although most life in tropical waters is concentrated around the coral reefs and the seagrass meadows,
不过还有些例外引人入胜.
there are some spectacular exceptions.
巴林的戈壁沙漠
The desert of Bahrain seems a very unlikely place
看上去不象是能有大量海鸟筑巢的地方
to find a crowded bustling colony of seabirds
可每年大约有10万只黑喉鸬鹚在这里繁殖
But every year, a hundred thousand socotra cormorants gather here to breed.
这里相当酷热
It's swelteringly hot
黑喉鸬鹚只好加速呼吸避免中暑
and only vigorous panting can prevent the birds from fatal overheating.
看上去这里不是抚育后代的好地方
This hardly seems a good place to rear young
不过至少没有陆基的捕食者
but at least, there are no land based predators here.
麻烦的唯一来源可能就是邻居了
The only source of trouble is likely to be the neighbors
所以每一个鸟窝都筑在邻居啄不到的地方
so each nest is built just beyond pecking reach
食物从哪里来呢?
But what about food?
这个荒凉沙漠远离温暖的浅海
There's only bare sand and the warm shallow sea beyond.
而且看上去也不能提供给鸬鹚足够的食物
Neither seem likely to produce enough nourishment to support bird life on this scale.
答案是刮起的大风
The answer is blowing in the wind.
夏马风卷起沙尘 吹向波斯湾
Sand whipped up by Shamals offshore winds blows into the seas of the Arabian Gulf.
风把带着养分的沙尘,像肥料一样撒进大海, 把这片浅海变成了富饶的渔场.
With the grains come nutrients, which act as fertilizer and they transform the shallow sea into a rich fishing ground
矛盾的是 热浪朝天的的阿拉伯半岛
So, paradoxically, it's the roasted sands of Arabia that prevent the gulf
阻止海湾变成另一个海中沙漠
from being another desert in the sea.
小座头鲸现在有五个月大了
The whale calf is now five months old.
它的身材也大了一倍 在热带托儿所的日子也到头了
He's almost doubled in size and his days in his tropical nursery are coming to an end.
在这个地方长大温暖而安全
It has been a warm and safe place in which to grow up
但在这里他的母亲无法吃到任何东西
but there's nothing to eat here for his mother.
她在过去的八个月里一直靠储存的脂肪存活
She has been living off her fat reserves for the last eight months
现在她临近饿死的边缘
and she's close to starving.
她现在必须离开 趁她还有足够的能量 在漫漫征途之中
She must leave now, while she still has enough energy to guide and protect her calf,
来指导和保护她的幼子
on the long voyage ahead.
横越热带 座头鲸调头离开赤道
All across the tropics, humpbacks are heading away
走向富饶而气候温和的南半球和北半球海域
from the Equator towards the rich temperate seas of both the southern and the northern hemispheres.
这些是更冷、更狂暴、更多危险的水域
These are colder, rougher, and more dangerous waters.
母鲸和小鲸鱼必须靠得很近
Mother and calf must stay close.
他们可以通过拍打海面 制造超越海洋轰鸣的的声音
They can send sound signals to one another, above the roar of the ocean
以此相互传送声音信号
by slapping fins on the surface.
在冬季 气候温和的海域被风暴肆虐着
In winter, the temperate seas are lashed by violent storms.
湍流激起海水 将深处的养分搅上来
The turbulence stirs the water, and draws nutrients up from the depths
但只有养分并不能维持生命
but nutrients alone can not support life.
还必须有阳光
There must also be sunlight.
春天 太阳高悬空中
In the spring, as the sun daily climbs higher in the sky
藻类开始生长
the algae start to grow.
旺盛的藻类占据着亚马逊雨林般大小的面积 它们将大海染绿
Blooms the size of the Amazon Rainforest turn the seas green.
单体藻类虽然很细小 但它们共同产生了我们大气中四分之三的氧气
Individually the algae are tiny but together, they produce three quarters of all the oxygen in our atmosphere.
藻类被一群让人困惑的生物吃掉
They're eaten by an array of bewildering creatures.
樽海鞘出现在浮游生物汤中
Salps appear in the plankton soup.
这些一个个单体组成的链条可长达15米
Individuals link together to form chains which can stretch for fifteen meters.
他们用汲取海水,在身体里过滤 分离出藻类及其他可食用微粒
Pumping water through their bodies they strain out algae and other edible particles.
栉水母在水中游弋,
Comb jellies cruise through the water.
它们也在这个季节性美汤里蓬勃生长
They too flourish in this seasonal soup
在很短的时间内,它们就能达到惊人的数量.
and for short periods, they appear in astounding numbers.
磷虾,一种小型虾类,如果按重量计算
Krill, shrimp like creatures. By weight they're the most
他们是地球上最多量的动物,一群就可达200万吨
abundant animals on the planet. A single swarm can contain two million tons of them
磷虾也为鱼提供了大量的食物
and that is a lot of fish food.
这片温和的浅海是地球上鱼类最密集的地区
The shallow temperate seas support the greatest concentrations of fish on our planet.
大量鱼群从海洋深处的冬歇地赶来
Huge shoals migrate from their overwintering grounds in the depths
在这片富饶海域进食
to feed in these rich waters.
鱼群也养育了世界上大多数海洋哺乳动物
It's these shoals that support most of the world's sea mammals.
海狮拥有捕鱼所需的敏捷和速度
Sea lions have all the agility and speed needed to collect what they want
看起来他们也喜欢这样做
and seemingly delight in doing so.
200条暗色斑纹海豚聚集在一起 紧密合作,尽情收获
Dusky dolphin, often in pods two hundred strong work together to reap the harvest.
它们将鱼群分成许多小群, 让猎人们更加易于处理.
They break up the shoals into smaller, more manageable balls, and all the hunters benefit.
直到夏至 海洋表面的养分全部被摄取
By midsummer, the surface nutrients have all been absorbed.
藻类死亡 食物链因此崩溃
The algae die and the food chain collapses.
然而在少数特别的地方
In a few special places, however
气候温和的海域维持这个生命水平贯穿整个夏季
the temperate seas sustain these levels of life throughout the summer.
在加利福尼亚沿海 洋流持续不断的
Along the coast of California, ocean currents carry a constant
把养分从海底 带到海平面上来
supply of nutrients up from the depths to the surface layers.
这种上升洋流给巨藻带来了大量养分 在夏日阳光照射下它们飞速生长
These upwellings fertilize forests of giant kelp, that thrive in the summer sunshine.
这片巨藻林有足有三层楼那么高
The algal towers are as high as a three story house
它们每天还能长半米
and they can grow by half a meter a day.
海藻中的生命充满戏剧性 跟其他森林一样
Life in the kelp is as full of drama, as in any other forest
但演员们仍不太为人知.
but the cast is less familiar.
一大群紫海胆正在发动进攻
An army of sea urchins is mounting an attack.
海胆们正在吃巨藻的固着器 把巨藻固定在石头上的重要装置
The urchin plague strikes at the kelp's holdfasts their crucial attachments to the rock.
固着器非常坚硬
Holdfasts are extremely tough,
但是每只海胆有5个锋利的牙齿 而且每隔几个月就换牙
but each urchin has five teeth, which are self sharpening and are replaced every few months.
海胆吃掉了大片的海藻森林 把它们变成了不毛之地.
Urchins fell vast areas of kelp forest creating clearings know as urchin barrens
无法形容的荒凉.
yet barrens is a poor description.
百万只无脊椎动物侵袭了海床
Millions of invertebrates invade the seabed.
这里有可怕的大型掠食动物
The most fearsome predator here is a giant.
向日葵海星长达1米 它喜欢吃蛇尾海星
The sunflower starfish is a meter across, with an appetite for brittle stars.
向日葵海星用触角来试探猎物
It uses it's feet to taste for prey.
在快速镜头下
When it's actions are speeded up,
可以清楚看到向日葵海星喜欢吃蛇尾海星
it becomes clear that the predator's fondness for the brittle stars
这与蛇尾海星快速逃离现场也是相吻合的
is almost matched by the brittle stars ability to get out of the way.
成群的饼海胆叠加起来组成防御阵线
Sand dollars flat sea urchins cluster together as a defense
不过好像在向日葵海星面前没有作用
But it doesn't seem to work against the sunflower starfish.
向日葵海星挤出它的胃 包住饼海胆直接消化其软组织
The predator extrudes it's stomach, and wraps it around it's victims liquefying their soft parts.
最后只剩下饼海胆的白色骨架.
Nothing is left of them, except their white skeletons.
加利福尼亚寒流是季节性洋流,相对较小.
The Californian upwellings are seasonal and relatively small
不过在南部非洲的大洋流带来的 充足食物能满足百万只海豹的需要
but in Southern Africa they're so big they create seas rich enough to support colonies of over a million seals.
本格拉寒流--沿南部非洲西岸流动
The Benguela Current sweeps along the western coastline of Southern Africa
给海洋表面带来充足养分
driving nutrient rich waters up to the surface
然后,在非洲南端(好望角)与 沿非洲大陆以南海域流动的厄加勒斯暖流汇合
and then, at the southern tip of Africa it meets the Agulhas Current, arriving from the east.
结果是,海洋养分更加丰富.
The result: even richer waters.
海豹在吃这里大量的鱼和枪乌贼(即鱿鱼)
The seals here thrive on a diet of fish and squid.
在这块海洋里,鱿鱼实际上要比鱼类多.
In temperate seas there may actually be more squid than fish.
这是宽褶鱿鱼
These are choker squid,
它们在厄加勒斯暖流经过的砂质浅海处产卵
and they lay their egg capsules in sandy shallows bathed by the warmer Agulhas Current.
每个卵囊都有100多条小鱿鱼
Each capsule contains a hundred tiny squid.
几天后它们长出一些色斑 等到成熟后
Within a few days they develop spots of pigment which, when they're adult,
就可以用这些色斑来互相联系
they will use to communicate with one another.
雌鱿鱼继续产卵
With females continuing to lay eggs
雄鱿鱼则忙于击退竞争对手而放松了警惕
and males still preoccupied with repelling rivals, the squid drop their guard.
黄貂鱼
Stingray.
短尾黄貂鱼身长可达2米
Short tailed stingray can be up to two meters across.
它是世界上最大的一种? 与之相称的还有它的胃口
They're the largest of all the stingrays, and they have appetites to match.
还有掠食者在游弋
Another predator is on the prowl.
南非虎头鲨
The aptly named ragged tooth shark.
虎头鲨可以长到3米长
Raggies grow to three meters long,
不过还有2倍于它的鲨鱼 在和它们一起分享这片水域
but they share these waters with a shark twice their size.
大白鲨
The great white.
地球上最大的掠食性鱼类
The largest predatory fish on the planet.
黎明时分,南非海狗离开聚居地去捕鱼
Each dawn cape fur seals leave their colony to go fishing.
要到达远海
To reach the open sea,
它们必须穿越一片狭窄的水域
they must cross a narrow strip of water
大白鲨就在那里逡巡
and that is patrolled by great whites.
每只海豹必须拼命游泳
Each seal is indeed swimming for it's life.
可大白鲨让人惊奇
The shark relies on surprise.
大白鲨的速度和力量来自体内高速的新陈代谢
The great white's turn of speed is powered by a high metabolism.
它们只呆在冰冷的海里 也只有大海才有充足的食物
They only thrive in cold temperate seas for only these waters contain sufficient food necessary
供这种贪婪的掠食者享用
to fuel such a ravenous predator.
当你朝南北两极旅行 更冷,更多风暴的海域才是更加富饶的
As you travel towards the poles north or south the colder, stormier seas can become even richer.
在南非和南极之间
Midway between South Africa and the South Pole
有一个与世隔绝的岛屿--马里恩岛
lies the isolated island of Marion.
岛屿位于气候恶劣的"咆哮西风带"
The island sits in the infamous "roaring forties"
不间断的大风把海底的养分送上来 从而给帝企鹅提供了丰富的食物
where incessant gale force winds draw nutrients up from the depths ensuring plenty of food for king penguins.
帝企鹅刚刚完成了3天的捕捞航行
The kings are returning from a three day fishing trip,
并给孩子们带来了食物
with food for their chicks
不过首先它们要通过拥挤的海滩
But first they must cross a crowded beach,
从巨大的,暴躁的海象间开出一条路来
threading their way between gigantic and bad tempered elephant seals.
在这块富饶的捕鱼圣地上 大约有20万只企鹅在这里繁殖
The two hundred thousand penguins breeding here are testament to the richness of the fishing.
小帝企鹅必须依靠它们的母亲至少一年 这给它们父母带来巨大的压力
King chicks are dependent on their mothers for over a year and this puts a great deal of pressure on the parents.
由于不能飞 企鹅必须步行穿越空旷的海滩
Being flightless, the returning penguins must cross the open beach on foot.
海狗,来到海滩繁殖并等待企鹅的到来
Fur seals, that have come to the beach to breed, are waiting for them.
通常海狗以磷虾为生
Fur seals normally live on krill
不过现在.它们可以从富含鲸脂的企鹅身上 获得意想不到的美味
but these have now acquired an unexpected taste for blubber rich penguins.
企鹅在海狗面前可能是轻量级选手
Penguins may be featherweights by comparison
但是企鹅有尖利的喙和易怒的性格
but they have razor sharp bills and a feisty character.
海狗可能会被啄瞎眼睛
The seal could easily lose an eye.
唯一的方法就是从背后抓住企鹅 不过企鹅也很清楚这一点.
The only safe way to grab a penguin is from behind, and the birds are well aware of that.
两种动物在这地形下都显得笨拙 不过企鹅更容易失败
Both animals are clumsy on this terrain but the penguin has the more to lose.
成功了!
Made it.
有三分之二的企鹅能在海狗的攻击下逃生 顺利到达永远吃不饱的小企鹅身边
Two out of three penguins survive the seal attacks and succeed in reaching their ever hungry chicks.
座头鲸接近它们史诗般旅程的终点
The humpbacks are nearing the end of their epic journeys.
历时2个月,数千英里的跋涉 它们进入了两极的极地海洋
After two months and thousands of miles, they're entering the polar seas both in the north and the south.
在遥远的北方 寒冬终于过去
In the far north, winter is over at last
冰雪开始消融
and the ice is starting to melt.
阿拉斯加(美国)西部的 阿留申群岛是通向白令海的大门
The Aleutian Island chain running west from Alaska is the gateway to the Bearing Sea.
随着冰雪的消退,暴烈的天气 和汹涌的洋流把这片浅海搅得天翻地覆
With the retreating ice, rough weather and ferocious currents stir up these shallow seas.
再加上阳光,这种组合的产生了大量的养分
Add sunshine and the mix is spectacularly productive.
500万只水雉鸟 从澳大利亚飞行了近万英里来到这里
Five million shearwaters have flown almost ten thousand miles from Australia to get here.
总计约有8000万只海鸟到这里度夏
In all eighty million seabirds come here for the summer
到处都是世界上最伟大的聚集
the greatest concentration to be found anywhere on Earth.
座头鲸终于抵达
The humpbacks have finally arrived.
庞大的水雉鸟群大量捕食磷虾
The giant shearwater flocks hunt the krill swarms
有时它们潜到40米深
sometimes diving to depths of forty meters to reach them.
一头成年座头鲸每天能吃掉3吨磷虾
A large humpback eats three tons of krill a day.
夏季的极地海域是地球上最多产的
The polar seas in summer are the most productive on the planet
鲸鱼昼夜不停地在此进食
and the whales gorge themselves round the clock.
它们现在积累的脂肪
The fat reserves they lay down now
可以支持到明年再来
will keep them alive during the year to come
不过也可能不会再来了
but it may not always be this way.
鱼和磷虾的产量正在迅速减少 象这样的景象可能很快将成为历史
Fish and krill stocks are declining so rapidly that spectacles like this may soon be part of history.
一旦母鲸和小鲸到达他们的给养地 它们就要分开
Once the mother and calf have reached their feeding grounds, they will separate.
如果幸运的话 小座头鲸还要把从赤道到极地的史诗般旅程
With luck, the calf will make the epic journey across the oceans from equator to pole
重复70次
another seventy times
让我们在浅海之间来回巡游 赞叹于地球生命的丰富多彩.
cruising back and forth between the shallow seas where life proliferates so abundantly on our planet.